import { useEffect, useReducer } from "react";
import Header from "./Header";
import Main from "./Main";
import Loader from "./Loader";
import Error from "./Error";
import StartScreen from "./StartScreen";
import Question from "./Question";
import NextButton from "./NextButton";
import Progress from "./Progress";
import FinishScreen from "./FinishScreen";
import Footer from "./Footer";
import Timer from "./Timer";
const SECONDS_PER_QUESTIONS = 30;
const tempData = [
  {
    question: "Which is the most popular JavaScript framework?",
    options: ["Angular", "React", "Svelte", "Vue"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which company invented React?",
    options: ["Google", "Apple", "Netflix", "Facebook"],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "What's the fundamental building block of React apps?",
    options: ["Components", "Blocks", "Elements", "Effects"],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question:
      "What's the name of the syntax we use to describe the UI in React components?",
    options: ["FBJ", "Babel", "JSX", "ES2015"],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How does data flow naturally in React apps?",
    options: [
      "From parents to children",
      "From children to parents",
      "Both ways",
      "The developers decides",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "How to pass data into a child component?",
    options: ["State", "Props", "PropTypes", "Parameters"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "When to use derived state?",
    options: [
      "Whenever the state should not trigger a re-render",
      "Whenever the state can be synchronized with an effect",
      "Whenever the state should be accessible to all components",
      "Whenever the state can be computed from another state variable",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "What triggers a UI re-render in React?",
    options: [
      "Running an effect",
      "Passing props",
      "Updating state",
      "Adding event listeners to DOM elements",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: 'When do we directly "touch" the DOM in React?',
    options: [
      "When we need to listen to an event",
      "When we need to change the UI",
      "When we need to add styles",
      "Almost never",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
  {
    question: "In what situation do we use a callback to update state?",
    options: [
      "When updating the state will be slow",
      "When the updated state is very data-intensive",
      "When the state update should happen faster",
      "When the new state depends on the previous state",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "If we pass a function to useState, when will that function be called?",
    options: [
      "On each re-render",
      "Each time we update the state",
      "Only on the initial render",
      "The first time we update the state",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which hook to use for an API request on the component's initial render?",
    options: ["useState", "useEffect", "useRef", "useReducer"],
    correctOption: 1,
    points: 10,
  },
  {
    question: "Which variables should go into the useEffect dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Usually none",
      "All our state variables",
      "All state and props referenced in the effect",
      "All variables needed for clean up",
    ],
    correctOption: 2,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "An effect will always run on the initial render.",
    options: [
      "True",
      "It depends on the dependency array",
      "False",
      "In depends on the code in the effect",
    ],
    correctOption: 0,
    points: 30,
  },
  {
    question: "When will an effect run if it doesn't have a dependency array?",
    options: [
      "Only when the component mounts",
      "Only when the component unmounts",
      "The first time the component re-renders",
      "Each time the component is re-rendered",
    ],
    correctOption: 3,
    points: 20,
  },
];

const initialState = {
  questions: [],
  // loading, ready, error, active, finished
  status: "loading",
  index: 0,
  answer: null,
  points: 0,
  highScore: 0,
  timeRemaining: null,
};

function reducer(state, action) {
  switch (action.type) {
    case "dataReceived":
      return { ...state, questions: action.payload, status: "ready" };
    case "dataFailed":
      return { ...state, status: "error" };
    case "start":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "active",
        timeRemaining: state.questions.length * SECONDS_PER_QUESTIONS,
      };
    case "newAnswer":
      const question = state.questions.at(state.index);
      const correctAnswer = action.payload === question.correctOption;
      return {
        ...state,
        answer: action.payload,
        points: state.points + (correctAnswer ? question.points : 0),
      };
    case "nextQuestion":
      const canIncrease = state.index < state.questions.length - 1;
      return {
        ...state,
        answer: canIncrease ? null : state.answer,
        index: canIncrease ? state.index + 1 : state.index,
      };
    case "finishQuiz":
      return {
        ...state,
        status: "finish",
        highScore: Math.max(state.highScore, state.points),
      };
    case "restartQuiz":
      return { ...state, status: "ready", index: 0, answer: null, points: 0 };
    case "tick":
      const isFinished = state.timeRemaining - 1 <= 0;
      if (isFinished)
        return {
          ...state,
          status: "finish",
          highScore: Math.max(state.highScore, state.points),
        };
      return { ...state, timeRemaining: state.timeRemaining - 1 };
    default:
      throw new Error("Action Unkown");
  }
}

function App() {
  const [
    { questions, status, index, answer, points, highScore, timeRemaining },
    dispatch,
  ] = useReducer(reducer, initialState);

  const numQuestions = questions.length;
  const totalPoints = questions.reduce(
    (acc, question) => acc + question.points,
    0
  );

  useEffect(function () {
    // async function getQuestions() {
    //   try {
    //     // const res = await fetch("http://localhost:8000/questions");
    //     // const data = await res.json();

    //     dispatch({ type: "dataReceived", payload: data });
    //   } catch (err) {
    //     dispatch({ type: "dataFailed" });
    //   }
    // }

    // getQuestions();

    setTimeout(function () {
      dispatch({ type: "dataReceived", payload: tempData });
    }, 500);
  }, []);

  return (
    <div className="app">
      <Header />

      <Main>
        {status === "loading" && <Loader />}
        {status === "error" && <Error />}
        {status === "ready" && (
          <StartScreen numQuestions={numQuestions} dispatch={dispatch} />
        )}
        {status === "active" && (
          <>
            <Progress
              index={index}
              numQuestions={numQuestions}
              points={points}
              totalPoints={totalPoints}
              answer={answer}
            />
            <Question
              question={questions[index]}
              answer={answer}
              dispatch={dispatch}
            />
            <Footer>
              <Timer dispatch={dispatch} timeRemaining={timeRemaining} />
              <NextButton
                displayButton={answer !== null}
                dispatch={dispatch}
                isLastQuestion={index === numQuestions - 1}
              />
            </Footer>
          </>
        )}
        {status === "finish" && (
          <FinishScreen
            points={points}
            totalPoints={totalPoints}
            highScore={highScore}
            dispatch={dispatch}
          />
        )}
      </Main>
    </div>
  );
}

export default App;
